so you mentioned the other day about
sensors and sense objects
and you asked if can you be disturbed
is there any other can you be disturbed
if there wasn't
sense sense objects is there any form of
emotional disturbance
that doesn't involve doesn't involve the
sense objects or sensors or sense domain
objects or sensors or sense domain
which includes both sense sense objects
form a sense domain
domain and the senses but there is no
you can't experience anything else other
than senses sense objects from that
point of view
you can't that's all you know
yes yes that is your mode of being yeah
that's why
uh kamabawa the central being
it's not a it's not a being that arises
only when you engage with sensuality
like when the buddha talks about three
types of being you should think of them
as
is as three types of threshold
that your mind might be living on
so three types of domain
so you have the central being is the
most most common one
that's the most the broadest one that's
what everybody is in
then you have the rupa
rupa baba
the point is the the these three types
of being that the buddha talks about
three types of bhava
and yeah as you said like sometimes
people translate it as becoming
which again sort of comes and plays into
that view as if only when you are
engaging with
karma uh
that being is becoming but if you stop
engaging that being is not becoming no
you can be restrained for the rest of
your life
and not engage with centrality and still
be be within
the central domain within the domain of
the central bava
even if you're not engaging with chasing
the pleasures your mind is still on the
level of
of on the threshold of senses and sense
objects it hasn't
hasn't developed beyond that so your
mind is resting
either on the coursest which is central
domain or then more refined which is the domain
or then more refined which is the domain
of of matter
or even more refined which is the
formless domain but then even then
arahant would abandon any form
of being as in he wouldn't rest on any
form whether form of the senses form or
whether form of the senses form or
formless form
so to speak so so that's just to
illustrate the point that
if you're not free from sensuality your
mind is fully
within the being of sensuality that
doesn't mean
being of chasing the pleasures wildly no
just means
being within sense sense objects that is
your basis that is your world
that is your extent so from that point
of view
it is impossible for you to experience
any form of
emotion any form of feeling that it will
not be rooted
within upon that that very um
threshold that very sense sense object
bases so practically speaking that means
any disturbance and a single disturbance
because that's the whole point
of practice it's not to get the pleasure
but it's to free yourself from suffering
which is the ultimate pleasure
so any form of disturbance any form of
suffering is it possible to experience it unless
is it possible to experience it unless
it's within
sense sense or sense object or both
unless it's because of because of
something on that domain
any form of disturbance even if just
mental idea of something it's always
going to be
well boiled down to something you either
see hear
smell taste touch or something you would
have to see
hear smell taste touch okay when you
think about it
when you look at the content of those
thoughts those thoughts
that are now like causing a disturbance
is because they imply something
disagreeable of
seeing smelling hearing tasting or
touching so even the thoughts are within that
so even the thoughts are within that
central domain
and the content of them is still the
census
and the reason why that is this is
practically relevant
is because well the disturbance
any emotional discomfort always feels
like much more
[Music] but if you were to actually start seeing
but if you were to actually start seeing
it correctly also it's just the sight
that's that's what i'm resisting here it
always feels much more
yeah it always feels much more because
you always want to
well you're always trying to get rid of
it at face value so you basically imply
there is more to it than there is
that's why for another hunt who is fully
freed from any craving any resistance to
anything that arises on the level of
feeling in the scene there is just the scene in
in the scene there is just the scene in
the herd is just a hurt there isn't
anything else there and there never was
so in the pain is just the pain well in
the well again
in the pain there is just the pain show
from the point of your feeling but you
want to see that pain
is rooted upon something of the
sense kind side sound smell taste touch
it has to be
see say you you experience a disturbance
on account of somebody died
you see you will never see them again
so change in the domain of sight
or you'll never talk to them again you
never get to touch them again
so it's basically just deprived
deprivation of the senses
oh certain things have changed now and
you cannot experience in the same way
so that form that you used to see of
that person now cannot be seen
so an account of that site that has
changed you grieve
you're disturbed
but it is just the side so and always
was the site
would you be able to experience love
infatuation attachment whatever
towards anyone if you've never seen them
if you've never heard them if you never
touch them
would you be able to even think about it
no impossible
and it would have said that in in many
other suta just in different slightly
different contexts but there was always
a point can you have
uh can you he asked that man can you
experience lust or
things they were not seen heard not not
basically experience through senses isn't that
experience through senses isn't that
it's impossible to experience those
things that i've never seen
so then it is ah so things you've never
seen you can't experience last which
means things you've seen
your lust is fully circumstantial
because you've seen them but you could
have not seen them and you will not see
them so not just that kind of puts the
so not just that kind of puts the
objects of your senses in perspective
but puts your own senses back into
perspective as well
yeah my my own senses are disintegrating
slowly failing so i if if sense objects are not
failing so i if if sense objects are not
changed well the senses will change
either way not not both can remain
unchanged for the duration of your lifetime let
for the duration of your lifetime let
alone longer than that
as in this will last forever impossible
[Music] and you experience change constantly on
and you experience change constantly on
a daily basis
but you just keep focusing on the
pleasant change
when you think about change oh it's but
whenever you suffer
you suffer a kind of unpleasant change
either way change is there
so if you
if you are longing for a site
do you reflect you say to yourself well
that's just a sight
well i you want to ask yourself why
why are you saying that to yourself now
because i'm longing for it i'm suffering
yeah so longing is unpleasant so are you
saying that's just a sight so you don't
experience this pleasure yeah so that i can force
this pleasure yeah so that i can force
that idea
into my mind yeah so but that's you can
do it literally anything from any suta
if you do it like that you'll be doing
it wrongly although you're doing what
the sutta says
you're not doing it rightly so you will
not get the benefit from it
so you shouldn't be trying to get rid of
it the reason experience
the threshold is you are emotionally
engaged with the domain of sight
you're longing for it longing for it
wanting it not wanting it either way you
and the site
there is a relationship there on account
of which you feel
so you have to accept that as a starting
point not
i must get rid of this i must deal with
this no that is that has arisen on its
own so the only thing you must do is
understand it
when i say understand it i don't even
understand some hypothesis that arises
on account of it understand the nature
of that relationship
what is the nature of longing for a
sight well it implies the necessity of
your sense basis as in your eyes so it
implies the presence of your
of your eyes that pressure to go and see
something you want
or the pressure to avoid seeing
something you don't want
if you don't have the eyes none of
that's applicable anymore
so part of the understanding that
relationship is understanding the
gratuity of eyes
eyes see you're subjected to what they
see but do you have control over your eyes
but do you have control over your eyes
remind yourself of that context of
these eyes are these lumpy flesh balls
of flesh
in the world like all these other random
things on account of which i get
sights that's it but i have no
fundamentally i have no control over my
eyes in the sense of
i'm not their owner i can't prevent them
from suddenly not working anymore or seeing
suddenly not working anymore or seeing
something or seeing something i don't
want to see exactly
see if you were truly a master you would
only see things you want to see
you would be the master of that which
arises on account of the eyes which is
sights and yet
here you are grieving on account of
sights so again when we talk about
so again when we talk about
understanding it's not about discerning
some some theoretical relationship and
some theoretical relationship and
meaning
or secret it's literally drilling in
repetitively the obviousness of the
nature of these things
but i say the obviousness because it's
obvious and because it's obvious people
don't think about it
but it's not enough to see that it's
obvious that eyes are not yours
you need to now keep repeat that same
obvious seeing
well for as long as you have lost in
regard to sides left
because if you understood that correctly
it's impossible to experience lust
towards sights or disturbance
any form of disturbance yeah so it's
because you don't see the nature
of your senses because you haven't
understood it that's why it's still
disturbed so
the obviousness of it should not fool
you into thinking okay i got this what
next yeah i got it does that mean i'm free
yeah i got it does that mean i'm free
from sensuality
no and a sight disturbed me exactly the
future you have to keep reflecting
and that's what i would always say yes
you practice you have insights
things start making sense but that's
only part of the picture the other part
is
you keep asking yourself okay so can
another reason sensuality arise now in
me
does the reason sensuality last less
less like
for a shorter amount of time is my mind
quicker to freeze
all of these things you reflect to see
oh am i actually free or is this kind of
a temporary i made sense out of anything
and i got a relief
because of that experience so you want
to you want that understanding
to also prevent you from being disturbed
in the future not just freeing you from
whatever was disturbing you while you
were thinking about it
so once like your eyes what you see
do not disturb me you mean my eyes do
not disturb you yeah
yes yeah so is that but understanding
my eyes well that same way yeah exactly
you want to start seeing your eyes
pretty much like other people's eyes
like a stranger it's just
your eyes is the closest to your point
of view than other people's eyes but
either way eyes are their sights are
there but yeah your eyes are not
more yours than my eyes are
they just uh closer they're closer in
their arrangement
whichever way you experience the world
and because of that
proximity oh this is mine because
there's nothing else between me and this
there is a lot in between me and your
eyes but with between me and my eyes there's
but with between me and my eyes there's
nothing in between it's just
i see that's why the sense bases
are always described in that kind of
negative terms like as absent so to
speak they're defined by things you see
you can't see your eyes but the eyes are
there because of which you see
you can't hear your ears
because there's nothing nothing in
between you nothing that you can
perceive between you and your son's bases and
between you and your son's bases and
that's why the ownership
of the entire dome world is rooted upon
the ownership of the senses
and the body
it's removing that ownership yeah
removing the ownership through seeing
that these things
operate on their own they don't even
know about you you don't exist for them
eyes don't know about van der mataneo
i just keep seeing that's all they see
keep avoiding the disagreeable keep
looking they agree or
but when you don't own them anymore
you see the nature they still will go
for the
what is agreeable to them yes and what
is disagreeable and what is disagreeable
yeah so because agreeable and disagreeable
so because agreeable and disagreeable
fundamentally does not require lust
but there is no lust without agreeable
or disagreeable
so agreeable and disagreeable is what
sensors do
you taking the ownership assuming the
ownership of the census you are then pulled by
of the census you are then pulled by
agreeable and repelled by disagreeable
as in there is lust there is a version
there there is delusion distraction there but
there is delusion distraction there but
you remove the ownership
there is no more lust towards agreeable
there is no more aversion towards
disagreeable and there is no more distraction towards
and there is no more distraction towards
neutral so what's stopping the eye from
going absence of lust
yeah yeah there's no there's no passion
i like see it's a
this is an agreeable sight and it stops
there it's your mind infected with lust that
it's your mind infected with lust that
then wants more
wants to taste it wants to touch it
wants to have it wants to whatever
if it's disagreeable wants to destroy it
wants to kill it
those are not senses anymore now it's
you completely blowing up on account of
it
right but that's lust and aversion so
there is this still the basis of this
agreement oh there's still disagreeable
this is still agreeable but if you have
no lust
nor aversion that cannot become more oh
this is disagreeable
this is annoying harassing and it turn
away you turn away that's the end of it
but even then you don't turn away
because you're reversed towards it
because the only reason you're too
averse towards it is because you sort of
overreached in regard to your own senses
as yours
so what else is there to blame no it's
things that disturb their senses
but if your senses are not yours
you would not blame sense objects for
anything
so let's say a disagreeable sight arises
i'm not free from suffering hmm
so that's your starting point no the
discomfort yeah so first thing you do is
okay i must not
act out of trying to get rid of the
discomfort because that's going to be
another just acting out of a version even if
just acting out of a version even if
it's but i practice the dhamma well
the only way you can practice the dhamma
is to not be rooted in craving
and if you're trying to get rid of the
aversion that has arisen on a kind of
disagreeable sight
you are rooted in craving thus there
will be no dhamma you practice
it doesn't matter how much you think
about it so first
what is the present situation for you
well it's the disagreeable feeling on
account of
unpleasant sight or unpleasant feeling
on a kind of disagreeable sight
better yeah like i said before we've got
pain in the knee
there's a discomfort yeah discomfort
well i won't move
now because if i move i'm averse
no i'm craving to get rid of the pain so
i'll just stick with this pain now
you're craving to not get rid of the
pain either you're affected by pain
so what do i do then well first you
allow that thing to endure
so don't just blindly move sure if it's
a problem
but then you reflect there is discomfort
body is subject to discomfort is this
body mind to what extent is mine
well i'm not sure if it's mine or not
well if it's yours would you be
experiencing any
discomfort so it's clearly the the
the sort of the pathway
where body as sense organs experiences
corresponding senses
you are not privy to that so all you
have is
i meets the sites somewhere in the world
and then if you are aware of it you get
the corresponding pressure so to speak
corresponding pressure so to speak
contact
so the only reason you know that i has
met the site not because you witnessed i
meeting the sites which is how usually
mistaken misconception of how the
contact arises
no the only reason you know that is
because you're already pressured on
account of the pressure of the visual
you know that eyes have seen
and that eyes and seeing you cannot get
in between that
even if you shut your eyelids you're
seeing the inner side of your eyelid
so eyes are always seeing and it's
inconceivable for you
to prevent eyes from seeing so how can
then that be
thoroughly in any shape or form yours
when you don't even know
how these things come together and
you're only subjected as i said to the
pressure resulting of it
and by the way that pressure is because
you already gratuously
foolishly own it
on that which is invisible to you pretty
much
so there you go plenty of things to
reflect upon
correctly without trying to get rid of
that uncomfortable
pressure off the disagreeable sights
because that's what feeling is
pressure pressure to its pleasure
refresh to its pain
away from pain pressure towards oblivion
so the body will still move away so it's
painful it'll shift
well yeah exactly will shift yeah and
you wouldn't have to overthink it
oh look the body moved because the knee
was hurting
yeah and i didn't even think about it it
doesn't need you he doesn't he never did
i said that before it's you are like
that uh
hey i was an unwanted guest but
you're you're a guest in this party
that's not even nobody
else knows you even there no one cares
that you're there
well it's the first one is right it's
not that no one cares because i don't
care you're invisible you're invisible to
you're invisible you're invisible to
insane the five aggregates
take any of your aggregates like you
don't exist for them
and it's because of that they're not
100's possible in the first place